https://youtu.be/VBNqikQF0GI
https://youtu.be/VBNqikQF0GI huongha.169_2/7/2016
Let's talk first about water.
Đầu tiên, hãy bàn về nước.
In 2007, the World Bank reported that water problems
Năm 2007, ngân hàng Thế Giới báo cáo rằng vấn đề về nước
led to an estimated loss of over 2% of China's GDP.
dẫn đến thất thoát hơn 2% GDP Trung Quốc.
China's per capita water resources are only 28%
Lượng nước bình quân đầu người chỉ bằng 28%
of the global average, which is one of the lowest levels in the world.
so với trung bình toàn cầu, nằm trong mức thấp nhất của thế giới.
The 20% of the world's population that lives in China survives on less than 7%
20% dân số thế giới sống tại Trung Quốc sống dựa vào chưa đến 7%
of global freshwater resources.
lượng nước sạch toàn cầu.
And yet, China's expanding economy has meant an increasing demand for water.
Sự mở rộng của kinh tế Trung Quốc đồng nghĩa với tăng nhu cầu về nước.
Scarcity of water has affected urban areas and agriculture.
Khan hiếm nước đã ảnh hưởng tới thành thị và nông nghiệp.
2/3 of China's cities-- and there are 660 labelled as city's-- already lack
2/3 các thành phố - 660 thành phố - đã thiếu
sufficient water resources to support further growth.
nguồn nước cung cấp cho các phát triển về sau.
Agriculture, meanwhile, accounts for about 2/3
Trong khi đó, nông nghiệp tiêu thụ 2/3
of national water consumption, and half of China's water pollution
nguồn nước quốc gia, và gây ô nhiễm 1/2 nguồn nước
through fertilizer runoff and livestock waste.
qua thất thoát phân bón và chất thải vật nuôi.
China relies heavily on groundwater for its water.
Trung Quốc chủ yếu dựa vào nguồn nước ngầm.
It supplies 70% of the drinking waters in the dry Northeastern
Nguồn nước này cung cấp 70% nước uống ở vùng khô phía Đông Bắc
and Northwestern parts of the country and over 40%
và Đông Nam, và hơn 40% nguồn nước
of the water used in farming.
được sử dụng trong trồng trọt.
But groundwater levels have dropped as quickly
Nhưng lượng nước ngầm đã nhanh chóng cạn kiệt
as a meter per year between the years 1974 and 2000 in north China.
khoảng 1 mét/năm từ 1974-2000 ở Bắc Trung Quốc
In urban areas, wells have been drilled into groundwater reserves
Ở các thành thị, các giếng khoan dẫn đến nước ngầm
as deep as one kilometer.
dự trữ sâu đến 1km.
Lakes have been shrinking over time.
Các hồ nước cạn dần.
The total lake area of Hunan, Hubei, Jiangxi, Anhui, and Jiangsu provinces
Tổng diện tích hồ ở các tỉnh Hồ Nam, Hồ Bắc, Giang Tây, An Huy và Giang Tô
decreased from about 30,000 square kilometers in 1949.
giảm từ khoảng 30 000 km vuông năm 1949.
It's hard to believe, but Hubei was once the province of 1,000 lakes.
Thật khó tin, nhưng Hồ Bắc khi xưa có 1000 hồ,
It's total lake area having shrunk to about 3,000 square kilometers
và diện tích của nó đã teo lại còn khoảng 3000 km vuông
from once 26,000 over the past century.
từ 26 000 km vuông ở thế kỉ trước.
And only one of its 26 remaining lakes containing water
Và chỉ 1 trong 26 hồ ở đây
considered safe for human consumption.
được xem là an toàn cho con người sử dụng.
China's largest freshwater lake-- Poyang Lake in Jiangxi province--
Hồ nước sạch lớn nhất Trung Quốc - Hồ Bà Dương ở tỉnh Giang Tây -
once covered an area of 3,500 square kilometers.
từng rộng 3500 km vuông,
Today, only 200 square kilometers are underwater.
giờ đây chỉ còn 200 km vuông nước.
Rivers in China have been drying up.
Các con sông ở Trung Quốc đã cạn dần.
China's first national census of water in 2013
Cuộc điều tra về nước năm 2013 ở Trung Quốc
reported that 28,000 rivers with catchment areas of 60 square miles
báo cáo rằng 28 000 con sông với hơn 60 dặm vuông
or more disappeared in the past 20 years alone.
đã biến mất trong 20 năm qua.
In the United States, a loss of the equivalent amount of river basin area
Ở Mỹ, nếu mất một diện tích nước tương đương
would entail the disappearance of the entire Mississippi river.
thì sẽ làm xoá sổ luôn cả con sông Mississippi.
Of the water resources that remain, the majority are now polluted.
Đa phần nguồn nước hiện tại còn lại giờ đã bị ô nhiễm.
In 2006, more than 70% of China's rivers and lakes were polluted.
Năm 2006, hơn 70% các con sông và hồ đã bị ô nhiễm.
In 2009, the Chinese Geological Survey showed that 90% of China's groundwater
Năm 2009, cuộc khảo sát địa chất cho thấy 90% nguồn nước ngầm
was polluted-- 60% of it seriously so.
đả bị ô nhiễm - 60% ở mức nghiêm trọng.
And in rural areas, the lack of clean piped water
Ở các vùng nông thôn, thiếu nước máy sạch
was a leading cause of mortality among young children.
là nguyên nhân tử vong chủ yếu ở trẻ nhỏ.
In 2012, it was estimated that more than 100 million Chinese still lacked access
Năm 2012, ước tính hơn 100 triệu người Trung Quốc
to safe drinking water and another 200 million lacked access
vẫn thiếu nước uống sạch và 200 triệu người khác
to quality sanitation.
thiếu điều kiện vệ sinh.